<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
<title>Two Types of Science: Basic Science and Applied Science</title>
<citation>OpenStax College, &#8220;Biology&#8221;, pp. 20-21. OpenStax College. 30 May 2013.</citation>
<url>http://cnx.org/content/col11448/latest/</url>
<info type="arise"><arise-info book="1" section="1" unit="1" firstpage="9"/></info>
<body>
The scientific community has been debating for the last few decades about the value of different types of science. Is it valuable to pursue science for the sake of simply gaining knowledge, or does scientific knowledge only have worth if we can apply it to solving a specific problem or to bettering our lives? This question focuses on the differences between two types of science: basic science and applied science.

Basic science or &#8220;pure&#8221; science seeks to expand knowledge regardless of the short-term application of that knowledge. It is not focused on developing a product or a service of immediate public or commercial value. The immediate goal of basic science is knowledge for knowledge&apos;s sake, though this does not mean that, in the end, it may not result in a practical application.

In contrast, applied science or &#8220;technology,&#8221; aims to use science to solve real-world problems, making it possible, for example, to improve a crop yield, find a cure for a particular disease, or save animals threatened by a natural disaster. In applied science, the problem is usually defined for the researcher.

Some individuals may perceive applied science as &#8220;useful&#8221; and basic science as &#8220;useless.&#8221; A question these people might pose to a scientist advocating knowledge acquisition would be, &#8220;What for?&#8221; A careful look at the history of science, however, reveals that basic knowledge has resulted in many remarkable applications of great value. Many scientists think that a basic understanding of science is necessary before an application is developed; therefore, applied science relies on the results generated through basic science. Other scientists think that it is time to move on from basic science and instead to find solutions to actual problems. Both approaches are valid. It is true that there are problems that demand immediate attention; however, few solutions would be found without the help of the wide knowledge foundation generated through basic science.
</body>
</document>
