<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
<title>A New Body Shape Index Predicts Mortality Hazard Independently of Body Mass Index</title>
<citation>Krakauer NY, Krakauer JC (2012) A New Body Shape Index Predicts Mortality Hazard Independently of Body Mass Index. PLoS ONE 7(7): e39504. doi:10.1371/journal.pone0039504
Retrieved from http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0039504 on 04 Oct 2016.</citation>
<url>http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0039504</url>
<info type="arise"><arise-info book="2" section="3" unit="3" part="2" firstpage="43"/></info>
<body>
According to the World Health Organization (WHO), overweight and obesity are increasing in prevalence and rank fifth as worldwide causes of death among risk factors, behind high blood pressure, tobacco use, high blood glucose, and physical inactivity. In high and middle income countries, where the prevalence of overweight and obesity among the adult population already exceeds 50%, overweight and obesity occupy third place as risk factors causing death, behind high blood pressure and tobacco use. WHO defined overweight as body mass index (BMI; weight divided by ) at or above , with obesity defined as  [1]. Guidelines published by the USA National Institutes of Health, using the same definition, considered that overweight and obesity are the second leading cause of preventable death in the USA, behind smoking [2].

These BMI-based obesity guidelines have been accompanied by doubt as to the validity of BMI as an indicator of dangerous obesity. BMI does not distinguish between muscle and fat accumulation [3]–[6], and there is evidence that whereas higher fat mass is associated with greater risk of premature death, higher muscle mass reduces risk [7]. As well, BMI does not distinguish between fat locations, when central or abdominal fat deposition is thought to be particularly perilous [8]–[11]. Waist circumference (WC) has emerged as a leading complement to BMI for indicating obesity risk. A number of studies have found that WC predicted mortality risk better than BMI [12]–[17]. A recent WHO report summarized evidence for WC as an indicator of disease risk, and suggests that WC could be used as a alternative to BMI [18].

A key limitation, mentioned in the WHO report, of using WC as a proxy for abdominal fat distribution is that it is sensitive to body size (height and weight) as well as to fat percentage and distribution. In fact, WC is highly correlated with BMI, to the extent that differentiating the two as epidemiological risk factors can be difficult [19]. According to a consensus statement on the clinical usefulness of WC [20], &#8220;Further studies are needed to establish WC cut points that can assess cardiometabolic risk, not adequately captured by BMI and routine clinical assessments.&#8221; Scaling WC via allometric analysis to produce a quantity that is independent of BMI offers one means of separating the impact on health of body shape (degree of central bulge, presumably correlating with abdominal fat deposits) from that of body size (as measured by height, weight, and BMI). In this paper, our objectives are (1) develop A Body Shape Index (ABSI) based on WC that is approximately independent of height, weight, and BMI; and (2) evaluate ABSI as a predictor of mortality across age, sex, ethnicity, and BMI categories in a population sample, compared to the conventional predictors BMI and WC.
</body>
</document>