<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
<title>Assessing the Impact of Water Filters and Improved Cook Stoves on Drinking Water Quality and Household Air Pollution: A Randomised Controlled Trial in Rwanda</title>
<citation>Rosa G, Majorin F, Boisson S, Barstow C, Johnson M, et al (2014) Assessing the Impact of Water Filters and Improved Cook Stoves on Drinking Water Quality and Household Air Pollution: A Randomised Controlled Trial in Rwanda. PLoS ONE 9(3):e91011. doi:10.1371/journal/pone.0091011
Retrieved from http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0091011 on 04 Oct 2016.</citation>
<url>http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0091011</url>
<body>
Environmental contamination at the household level is a major cause of death and disease, particularly among rural populations in low-income countries. Unsafe drinking water, together with poor sanitation, account for an estimated 0.9% of the global burden of disease and 0.3 million deaths [1]. Much of this disease burden is associated with diarrhoea, which alone accounts for 10.5% of deaths in children under 5 years in low-income countries [2]. Household air pollution (HAP) from biomass fuel smoke has been linked to increased risk of respiratory tract infections, low birth weight, exacerbations of inflammatory lung conditions, cardiac events, stroke, eye disease, tuberculosis, cancer and nutritional deficiencies [3]. The Global Burden of Disease (GBD) 2010 project found HAP from solid fuels to be responsible for 3.5 million premature deaths globally [1]. In this same assessment, smoke from household cooking fuels was also responsible for another half a million premature deaths due to contributions to outdoor air pollution [1]. These environmental hazards are aggravated among rural inhabitants of sub-Saharan Africa who are more likely to rely on unsafe water supplies and cook using biomass fuels on inefficient stoves [4]–[6].

Inefficient cookstoves also present substantial economic, developmental and environmental costs. At the household level, poverty is exacerbated and time spent at school is reduced by the burden of collecting more fuel for boiling drinking water and cooking [7]. Individuals, households and governments bear the cost of expenditures for seeking treatment of enteric and respiratory infections. Cookstove emissions also contribute to greenhouse gas and black carbon emissions, and in some cases the fuel harvesting can result in denuding of forests [8], [9].

With a population of 10.5 million and a density of 412 persons per sq. km, Rwanda is the most densely populated country in East Africa [10]. Eighty per cent of the population of Rwanda lives in rural areas and is engaged in agriculture [11]. Despite significant progress over the last decade, 57% of the population is living below the poverty line, 37% of them living in extreme poverty [11]. While a large proportion of the rural population has access to improved water sources (71.2%), mainly through protected springs, only 2.2% of rural areas have water on their premises [12], resulting in an increased risk for drinking water contamination during transport and storage [13]. Almost all of rural Rwanda (99.0%) relies on biomass for their cooking needs [12]. Morbidity and mortality are largely dominated by communicable diseases, including HIV/AIDS, acute respiratory infections, diarrhoeal diseases, intestinal parisitoses, and malaria [14]. Among deaths of children under 5, pneumonia accounts for 20% and diarrhoea for 12% [15].

In an effort to reduce the disease burden in rural Rwanda, decrease poverty associated with expenditures for fuel, and minimize the impact of greenhouse gases from inefficient combustion of biomass in low-efficiency stoves, the Rwanda Ministry of Health (MiniSante) and the Rwanda Environmental Management Authority (REMA) have partnered with DelAgua Health (implementer) to design, deploy and evaluate the impact of a project that will deliver and promote the use of advanced water filters and high efficiency cookstoves to lower-income households in Rwanda. Prior to initiating the full campaign, the implementer with the Ministry of Health undertook a pilot distribution of filters and cookstoves to approximately 2200 households in 15 villages in 11 of the country&apos;s 30 districts. We conducted this study in three of those villages in order to assess the uptake of the intervention and its impact on drinking water quality and household air pollution.
</body>
</document>